Guide to the Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 Records WAG.132
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 Records
1944-1999
1976-1987
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America. Local 1153 (Valhalla, N.Y.)
Kosar, Andy
Algiere, Mary Lou
WAG.132
7.75 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons and 7 folders in a shared box.
Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 was chartered in 1975, after more than 500 members of the Manhattan-based Local 1150 petitioned for a new local to represent American Telephone & Telegraph's Long Lines (long distance) employees working in the White Plains and Mount Kisco area. The jurisdiction granted to Local 1153 compromised Westchester, Rockland, Orange and Putnam Counties in New York; and for the Construction Department only, all of New England, New Jersey and New York. But the majority of the Local's members are located in White Plains. Local 1153 has taken a strong stand on many issues, including job losses, job pressures, seniority rights, the creation of new job titles, health and safety, and discrimination based on sex and race. The collection reflects the Local's aggressive stance in bargaining, its role in the 1983 strike, and its criticism of many features of AT&T Divestiture.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Andy Kosar, president of the Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 in 1992. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1992.003 and 1992.009. Additional materials were donated by CWA, Local 1153 president Mary Lou Algiere, in 2005.
The accession numbers NPA.1993.021, NPA.1994.003 and NPA.2006.069 are also associated with this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 was chartered in 1975, after more than 500 members of the Manhattan-based Local 1150 petitioned for a new local to represent American Telephone & Telegraph's Long Lines (long distance) employees working in the White Plains and Mount Kisco area. The jurisdiction granted compromised Westchester, Rockland, Orange and Putnam Counties in New York; and for the Construction Department only, all of New England, New Jersey and New York. But the majority of Local members are located in White Plains. Like Local 1150, 1153 consists of three sections: Plant (construction and maintenance), Traffic (operators) and Administrative (clerical). Since 1975 the Local has had four presidents: Paul J. Marley (served 1975-1981), Eleanore Collins (1981-1984), Andy Kosar (1984-1999), and Mary Lou Algiere (2000- ). Local 1153 has taken a strong stand on many issues, including job losses, job pressures, seniority rights, the creation of new job titles, health and safety, and discrimination based on sex and race. The collection reflects the Local's aggressive stance in bargaining, its role in the 1983 strike, and its criticism of many features of Divestiture.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials documenting the founding of Local 1153 in 1976, minutes of the Executive Board, General Membership, Stewards and Committee on Equity meetings, as well as correspondence from Local 1153 Presidents, other Communications Workers of America Locals, and the national organization. Also included is material pertaining to bargaining, elections, AT&T labor relations, health and safety, and discrimination. Approximately 130 photographs document social events, rallies and conventions.
Note: The collection contains some materials from the period before 1975, when the White Plains area was still part of CWA Local 1150.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series, and in chronological order within topics.
Series I: Charters and Bylaws (1975-1996)
Series II: Minutes (1976-1995)
Series III: Correspondence (1965-1994)
Series IV: General Files (1944-1999)
Series V: Photographs (1979-1987)
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
OH 026 Communications Workers of America, Oral History Collection
WAG 124 and WAG 124.1 Records of the Communications Workers of America
WAG 059 Records of Communications Workers of America, Local 1150
WAG 117 Records of Communications Workers of America, District 1
WAG 089 Papers of Eleanore Collins
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Affirmative action programs -- United States.; Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- United States.; Telecommunication -- Employees -- United States.; White Plains (N.Y.); Correspondence.; Financial records; Discrimination in employment.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Corporate divestiture -- United States.; Transcripts.; Arbitration, Industrial.; Legal documents.; Collective labor agreements -- Telecommunication.; Company unions -- Telecommunication.; Photographs.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Labor unions -- Elections -- United States.; Strikes and lockouts -- Telecommunication.; Affirmative Action programs.; New York (N.Y.).; Labor unions -- Officials and employees.; Labor unions -- Contract administration.; Labor unions -- Political activity -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Communications Workers of America; Communications Workers of America. Local 1173; AFL-CIO; American Telephone and Telegraph Company -- Employees; Kosar, Andy; Marley, Paul J.; Collins, Eleanore, -1994; Kosar, Andy; Algiere, Mary Lou
- Series I: Charters and Bylaws, 1975-1996
  - Bylaws, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bylaws: Motions, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Charters (photocopies), 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Formation and Early History, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Organization Charts, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Minutes, 1976-1995
  - Central Labor Council, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Equity, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Downstate Ad Hoc AT&T Locals Committee, Nov 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Membership Meeting-Strike Authorization Vote, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - New York State Assembly Labor Committee, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Test and Inspection Feedback, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Outside Construction Workers Meeting, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Quality Work Life (QWL) Steering Committee, Oct 1988-Nov 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - QWL Steering Committee, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stewards Meetings, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Workplace of the Future, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1965-1994
  - Collins, Eleanore C., 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Kosar, Andy, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Kosar, Andy, Jan 1993-Apr 1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Kosar, Andy, May 1993-Dec 1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Kosar, Andy, Jan 1994-Jun 1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Kosar, Andy, Jul 1994-Dec 1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Marley, Paul J., 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Marley, Paul J., 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Local Vice-President, 1975-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Local Secretary, 1976-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Local Treasurer, 1976-1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Administrative Section Correspondence, 1965-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - District 1 Correspondence, 1976-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - District 1 Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - District 1 Correspondence, Jan 1989-Jun 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - District 1 Correspondence, Jul 1989-Dec 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - District 1 Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - District 1 Correspondence, Jul 1993-Dec 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - District 1 Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Faxes, Aug 1990-Dec 1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Faxes, Jan 1991-May 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Faxes, Jun 1991-Sep 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Faxes, Jan 1993-May 1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Faxes, Jun 1993-Dec 1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faxes, Jan 1994-Jun 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Faxes, Jul 1994-Dec 1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Grievance Letters, Jan 1994-May 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Grievance Letters, Jun 1994-Dec 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Local Headquarters Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Long-Lines Correspondence, 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Long Lines: National Director's Correspondence, 1966-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Members Correspondence, 1976-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Other Locals, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Other Locals, Jan 1990-Jun 1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Other Locals, Jul 1990-Dec 1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Other Locals, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Plant Section Correspondence, 1976-1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Social Committee Correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Stewards Correspondence, 1966-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Washington Correspondence, Apr 1994-Jul 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Washington Correspondence, Aug 1994-Dec 1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series IV: General Files, 1944-1999
  - 440 Hamilton Avenue: Phase II Master Plan, Dec 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Alliance for Employee Growth and Self Development, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Alliance Training, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Arbitration Awards, 1989-1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Arbitration Cases, 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Arbitration: Lost, 1986-1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Arbitration: Lost, 1996-1999 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Agreements-Contracts, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - American Telephone and Telegraph (AT&T), 1970-1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - AT&T Communications (ATTCOM), 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - AT&T Information Systems (ATTIS), 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Bargaining, 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Benefits, 1975-1981 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Blood Drive (Harassment Complaint), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Budget, 1981-1987 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Coalition of Black Trade Unionists, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Charter Review, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - City of Hope, 1976-1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Committee on the Future, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - CWA Organizer, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Community Services, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Computer Technician-New Job Title, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Conferences: CWA District 1, 1978-1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Conferences: Legislative, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Conferences: Long-Lines Presidents, 1977-1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Construction Department, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Convention-National CWA, 1976-1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Convention-National CWA, Special, Mar 1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Cornell University-Westchester Labor Studies Program, 1976-1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Customer Service Engineering, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Downstate Ad Hoc Committee Meeting, New Orleans, Aug 1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Discrimination, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Divestiture, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Education Department, CWA, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Elections, 1976-1987 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Employee Counseling/Assistance Programs, 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, 1976-1982 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Finances, 1976-1984 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Flex Time, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Force Adjustments, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Grievances, 1980-1983 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Health and Safety, 1976-1993 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Information Bulletin, 1973-1981 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Information Tapes, 1976-1984 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Information Tapes, 1996-1998 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW), Local 3, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Job Descriptions, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Job Descriptions, 1974-1984 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Job Evaluations, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Job Losses-White Plains, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Job Pressures, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Legislative-Correspondence and Information, 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Legislative-Correspondence and Information, 1979-1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Legislature, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Local Newsletter, 1992-1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Local Tape Messages, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Local Tape Messages, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Media Funds, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Memorandum of Agreement, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - National Black Communications Coalition, 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - News From CWA: District 1, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Newsletter, 1977-1984 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - New York Council for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH), 1990 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - New York State Department of Labor, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Nurses-Organizing, 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA), 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Office Employees International Union-Local 1150 Agreement, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Officers Training Class, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Organizing Committee, 1978-1981 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Organizing-Training Manual, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Picnic-Incident with Police, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Public Relations, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Quality of Work Life (QWL), 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Retired Members, 1977-1984 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Sales Specialist-New Job Title, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Scholarship Fund, 1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Seating Plan, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Sexual Discrimination/Harassment, 1976-1981 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Strike, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Strike-Trial Court, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Technology Change Committee (CWA/AT&T Long Lines), 1976-1983 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Telecommunications International Union, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Telecommunications Policy, 1976-1983 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - United Way, 1977-1985 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Upgrade and Transfer, 1974-1984 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Wages and Hours, 1970-1984 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Westchester-Putnam Central Labor Body, 1989-1993 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Western Electric Strike/Long Lines Suspension-1975, 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - White Plains-Agitation for Separate Local, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Women's Concerns, 1974-1984 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Workers' Compensation, 1981-1985 (Box 6, Folder 40)
- Series V: Photographs, 1979-1987
  - Annual Gala, 1st, 1979 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 1)
  - Campaign: Job Pressures, 1979 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 2)
  - Christmas Party, 1987 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 3)
  - Convention, CWA International (Miami Beach, Florida), 1987 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 4)
  - Marley, Paul J.: Portrait, circa 1976 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 5)
  - Picnic (Includes Eleanore Collins), circa 1983 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 6)
  - Strike (AT&T): Rallies, 1986 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Archived Website, Feb 26, 2009-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 was chartered in 1975, after more than 500 members of the Manhattan-based Local 1150 petitioned for a new local to represent American Telephone & Telegraph's Long Lines (long distance) employees working in the White Plains and Mount Kisco area. 1153 consists of three sections: Plant (construction and maintenance), Traffic (operators) and Administrative (clerical). Local 1153 advocates for many issues, including job losses, job pressures, seniority rights, the creation of new job titles, health and safety, and discrimination based on sex and race. The website contains by-laws, bargaining reports, other reports, event listings, and contracts.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.